{
  "reference_number": "9372",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "\"Domestic emissions\" should include emissions from international freight and travel, especially cruise and container ships coming to\n New Zealand and spending time here. It should also include the emissions caused elsewhere in the production of goods imported to\n New Zealand in countries such as China or India. We should not be able to meet a target using trade offs with other countries."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only to strengthen the provisions or bring the target forward (to 2040, for example). A different government should not be able to\n\n extend the target beyond 2050 or weaken the provisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The five (or six) -year-period planning should cover the whole period between the current time and 2050, and beyond in fact. 15\n\n years is not long-term enough. 30 years is a full generation and we should be thinking ahead to the next three generations at least.\n The planners for zero emissions now should be thinking at least 30 years ahead. Five six-year periods would make more sense than\n six of five years, as we have a three-year electoral cycle. Five year plans might suit the extreme short-term thinking of the business\n\n community, but this is not about dealing with cycles of business development and short term profit making. Any decent investor, farm\n or business should be thinking in decades, not five-year periods - in fact the phenomenon of human-induced climate change must\n show businesses and governments finally that short term nationalistic thinking got us into this and only a change to long-term\n\n thinking on a global level will get us out of it. We have to move to generational planning and planetary cycles of weather."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "This question assumes that the responder has agreed with the proposal to plan only 15 years ahead. For that reason, I say no,\n though I agree that a government should be able to revise plans in the light of current developments, but never to reduce efforts to\n\n reach the target, and only to strengthen and expand provisions for reducing emissions by whatever means."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The exceptional circumstances should be specified and there should be no possibility to dilute or weaken provisions, especially not\nin response to lobbying for short-term vested interests.The current oil and gas exploration/production situation is a good example of\nhow the government will be pressured by those who can only think in the short term."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "If equal weight is given to assessed impacts on the current economy etc, then decisions will be made which favour the status quo\n\nand there will be no progress (see above comment). The Climate Commission should be advocating for measures which may radically\nchange the status quo. It should not be hampered by the spurious arguments which will be put forward by the many vested\n\ninterests.which operate by making short term gain with no accountability. Climate change is radical and hugely destructive. Only\nradical measures will allow us to counter it at all. Opportunities will arise, and government may need to borrow to support changes in\n\ndirection. The CC should work towards the agreed outcome, keeping to 1.5% as an absolute maximum increase in temperature. That\nis the single criterion which should be applied. Agriculture's contributions to carbon emissions should be fully included in the\nreduction measures."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Iwi, cultural communities, councils, international partners, SOEs, business and industry groups including farming, forestry, fishing,\ntourism, mining and so on, as well as research and development. The single most important issue is that everyone needs to\nunderstand the need for radical change in our lives. That means meaningful and consistent education for everyone at every level\n\nabout the changes and the provision of incentives for people to adopt new habits. All institutions with any sort of authority need to be\ncompletely on board - police, defence forces, education, health, all local government, and representatives of migrant communities,\n\nand tourists."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think that the Climate Commission should have an arm's-length decision-making role, or at least it should be very difficult for the\ngovernment to override or ignore the proposals. Just advising and monitoring is not enough. We have seen enough of the damage\n\ngovernments can do to the climate when they have no commitment to the environment but concern themselves with the economy\nas they perceive it. The Climate Commission should have the independence and authority of bodies like the Auditor-General's office\nand be suitably staffed with people who have the experience, knowledge, global connections and ethical convictions to create\n\nproposals for action which will deliver the agreed goals. If necessary, the Government should be forced to account before a suitable\ncourt for any failure to adopt such proposals."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "These qualities, but also: proven depth of knowledge and experience of climate change policy in international contexts at\ngovernmental, institutional and personal levels, where climate change is understood and analysed. Connection to international\n\nnetworks which have long worked in this field. Deep knowledge of ongoing and previous scientific research Proven commitment to\nthe targets and goals No connection to business interests or any vested interests Proven principled behaviour No National Party\naffiliations (the National Party refused for 9 years to acknowledge or act on climate change)"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "\"the scope, scale and content of the national climate change risk assessment and adaptation plan\" Comments: Scope: national and\n\nlocal government Scale: comprehensive Content: Should specify how all essential services and functions can be once again\ncoordinated with proper accountability Councils and government are responsible for the safety and security of the citizens and\n\nresidents and should not outsource essential services to private contractors. If privatisation of essential services is allowed to\ncontinue, we can forget about making plans, as they will not succeed. Taxes and rates should pay for services directly, and then we\n\ncan plan and monitor."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "All structures, public or private, should analyse, report and share this information in an online information bank."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am old enough to remember living in a non-plastic, non-touristic New Zealand, where milk and houses were cheap and affordable\n\nand good quality, university was free, medical care was almost free, cars were expensive and rare, and we had many local industries\nproducing good quality goods. New Zealand families could afford to travel around New Zealand, though not overseas, so we grew to\nknow and love our country. There were trains and ships as well as roads and cars. We hadn't embarked on the disastrous dairy\n\nexpansion at that point, but we knew that the world was beginning to be in crisis. If we had had governments then who had listened\nto the warnings, we wouldn't be in this situation now. We could have made changes in energy production then. There was new\n\ntechnology for wind energy, that was not adopted, there were new building techniques that used fewer resources, that were not\nadopted. There were radical moves that took the country into a new world of unimagined wealth for a few, inequity and poverty for\n\nmany, cheap goods, luxury goods, cheap travel and overall huge debt, all of which has been killing the planet over time. It is unlikely\nthat this government or any other in the world will take the truly radical steps needed to address at least the current situation\n\neffectively. But we can hope, for our grandchildren and great-grandchildren's sake."
    }
  ]
}
